Guide to the Oscar J. Falnes Papers MC.135
New York University Archives
- Series IV: Personal
  - One View Master Reels, undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Photographs -- Family, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Photographs -- Family, undated; 1950 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Photographs -- Family and Travel, 1966 December (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Photographs -- New York and Travel, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Photographs -- New York and Travel, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Photographs -- Scandinavia, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Photographs -- School, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Photographs -- Travel, undated; 1939-1947 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Photographs -- Travel, 1947-1948 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - The Seville --11 Cornelia Residence (sketches), undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Slides -- Denmark, Belgium and Netherlands IV, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Slides -- Italy II, undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Slides -- Norway V, undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Slides -- Norway VI, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Slides -- Sweden, France and Germany, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Travel -- Ephemera, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Travel -- Europe Postcard Views (1 of 4), undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Travel -- Europe Postcard Views (2 of 4), undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Travel -- Europe Postcard Views (3 of 4), undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Travel -- Europe Postcard Views (4 of 4), undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Travel -- Europe Postcards (1 of 4), undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Travel -- Europe Postcards (2 of 4), undated (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Travel -- Europe Postcards (3 of 4), undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Travel -- Europe Postcards (4 of 4), undated (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Travel -- Guides, 1949-1961 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Travel -- Guides and Other Miscellaneous, 1 of 2, 1955-1961 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Travel -- Guides and Other Miscellaneous, 2 of 2, 1939-1961 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Travel -- Guides from 1934 Trip to Europe, 1 of 2, 1928-1938 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Travel -- Guides from 1934 Trip to Europe, 2 of 2, undated, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Travel -- Loose Postcards (Denmark), undated (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Travel -- Loose Postcards (Denmark and Norway), undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Travel -- Loose Postcards (Great Britain, etc.), undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Travel -- Loose Postcards (Mixed), undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Travel -- Loose Postcards (United States), undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Travel -- Photo Guides, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Travel -- Receipts and Memorabilia, 1 of 2, 1947-1967 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Travel -- Receipts and Memorabilia, 2 of 2, 1947-1967 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Travel -- United States Postcards (1 of 4), undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Travel -- United States Postcards (2 of 4), undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Travel -- United States Postcards (3 of 4), undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Travel -- United States Postcards (4 of 4), undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Travel -- United States and Europe Postcards and Photos, undated; 1954-1956 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - W -- Notepad of Books Acquired, circa 1918-1925 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - W -- Spencer Apartment Residence, 1948-1977 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Wood Lake Centennial, 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - World War II Ration Book, circa 1941-1945 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Series V: Professional
  Series V contains materials from Falnes' professional activities unrelated to New York University, mostly his involvement in AHA and UNNRA.
  - AHA -- 1955 Baltic Conference, 1955-1956 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - AHA -- Conferences, 1965-1966 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference, 1955-1958 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference - Accommodations, 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference - Executive Secretary (Boyd C. Shafer), 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference - Program Committee (Arthur P. Whitaker), 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference - Program Committee (Carl E. Schorske), 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference - Program Committee (Charles Hallberg), 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference - Program Committee (David Donald), 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference - Program Committee (Edgar Johnson), 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference - Program Committee (Edmund S. Morgan), 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference - Program Committee (Eugene Boardman), 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference - Program Committee Memoranda (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference - Proposals and Correspondence A-C, 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference - Proposals and Correspondence D-G, 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference - Proposals and Correspondence H-L, 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference - Proposals and Correspondence M-R, 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - AHA -- 1957 Conference - Proposals and Correspondence S-Z, 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - AHA Editorials -- Correspondence, 1934-1949 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - AHA Editorials -- Correspondence, 1950-1965 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - AHA Editorials -- Correspondence, 1952-1970 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - AHA Editorials -- Correspondence, 1965-1986 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Contemporary Scandinavia - Universal Education and Visual Arts, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Government Employment, 1941-1946 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Lund Conference, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - National War College (1 of 2), 1955 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - National War College (2 of 2), 1955-1956 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - OSS, International Services of Information Foundation, and Other Miscellaneous, 1943-1976 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - School of Military Government, 1942-1943 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Travel Arrangements and State Department, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - UNRRA, 1944-1956 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - UNRRA -- A History of the Fellowship Program, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - UNRRA -- Certificate and Letter, 1947 July (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - UNRRA -- Event Photographs, circa 1946-1948 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - UNRRA -- Fellows, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - UNRRA -- Fellows Correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - UNRRA -- Fellows Memos and Field Reports, 1946-1947 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - UNRRA -- Fellowship Committee, 1944-1948 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - UNRRA -- Fellowship Committee Correspondence and Summaries, 1947-1967 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - UNRRA -- Fellowship Program Essay (1 of 2), 1948-1953 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - UNRRA -- Fellowship Program Essay (2 of 2), 1968 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - UNRRA -- Fellowship Program History (1 of 2), circa 1949-1967 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - UNRRA -- Fellowship Program History (2 of 2), circa 1949-1967 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - UNRRA -- Fellowship Section Budget, 1946-1947 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - UNRRA -- Reports and Correspondence (1 of 2), 1946-1947 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - UNRRA -- Reports and Correspondence (2 of 2), 1946-1953 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - UNRRA -- UN Miscellaneous, 1947-1968 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - New York University mug, undated (Box 20)
    ID Number: 522. Description: part of MC 135 (Oscar Falnes Papers). Creator/Donor/Subject: MC 135.
- Series VI: Subject Files
  Series VI contains research materials assembled by Falnes, mainly clippings.
  - Book and Publication Reviews (not by Falnes), 1961-1965 (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - British Imperialist Thought (Newcomb College Thesis), 1966 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Congo, 1955-1962 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Congo Historical Background (For Trip), 1882-1911 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Denmark, 1942-1948 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Imperialism (1 of 2), 1959-1986 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Imperialism (2 of 2), 1941-1963 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Maps of Germany, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Minnesota, 1949-1986 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Minnesota, Woodlake and Hanley Falls, 1950s-1980s (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Nationalism, 1927-1980 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - New York City Preservation and Development (1 of 4), 1971-1985 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - New York City Preservation and Development (2 of 4), 1961-1979 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - New York City Preservation and Development (3 of 4), 1952-1976 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - New York City Preservation and Development (4 of 4), 1933-1974 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - New York City Preservation and Development, 1960s-1980s (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Norway Clippings, 1926-1947 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Norwegian flag, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - NY Verd, 1978 November (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Racism (1 of 2), 1964-1982 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Racism (2 of 2), 1963-1964 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Romanticism (1 of 2), 1930-1985 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Romanticism (2 of 2), 1928-1975 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - World War II in Denmark, 1940-1963 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - World War II in Finland, 1939-1946 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - World War II in Norway (1 of 2), 1939-1945 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - World War II in Norway (2 of 2), 1939-1945 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - World War II -- Norwegian Publications (1 of 2), 1941-1944 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - World War II -- Norwegian Publications (2 of 2), 1941-1942 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - World War II in Scandinavia, 1943-1946 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - World War II in Sweden, 1939-1945 (Box 11, Folder 27)
- Series VII: Writings
  Series VII contains notes, drafts, essays and other written materials produced by Falnes.
  - Book and Article Reviews (1 of 2), 1933-1934 (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Book and Article Reviews (2 of 2), 1930-1962 (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - Book Reviews (1 of 3), 1931-1973 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Book Reviews (2 of 3), 1938-1965 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Book Reviews (3 of 3), 1965-1968 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Christian Lange Essay (1 of 2), 1969 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Christian Lange Essay (2 of 2), 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Charles Pearson Essay, 1952 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Charles Pearson (European Progress and 'Superior' Races) Essay, 1954-1958 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Diary of a Dying Empire Review, Undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Ethnicity Essay - Notes and Research, 1981-1986 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Ethnicity Essay, "On Both Sides of the Hyphen" -- Notes and Background, 1973-1983 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Fellowship Study, 1925-1927 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Grolier (1 of 2), 1960-1961 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Grolier (2 of 2), 1960-1975 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Grolier and Cowles Entries (Drafts, Rewrites and Notes), 1964-1973 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Grolier and Other Encyclopedia Entries (1 of 2), 1951-1970 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Grolier and Other Encyclopedia Entries (2 of 2), 1951-1970 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Grolier Original Drafts and Corrections (1 of 2), Circa 1958-1970 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Grolier Original Drafts and Corrections (2 of 2), Circa 1958-1970 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Lewis Caso Paper, circa 1920s (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Libelled Viking Fracas, 1930-1932 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Manuscript Reviews, 1947-1975 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Essays and Articles, 1935-1942 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - New York Times Editorials, 1948-1963 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Notes and Drafts -- A Fellowship in the Twenties 1926-1927 (1 of 3), 1926-1980 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Notes and Drafts -- A Fellowship in the Twenties 1926-1927 (2 of 3), 1926-1980 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Notes and Drafts -- A Fellowship in the Twenties 1926-1927 (3 of 3), 1926-1977 (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Abstracted Materials (1 of 3), 1917-1922 (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Abstracted Materials (2 of 3), 1923-1926 (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Abstracted Materials (3 of 3), undated (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Anarchism, Economics and Political Science, undated (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Baltic Peoples, 1950s-1960s (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Baltic Sea Rivalry-Early and Modern, 1945-1961 (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Baltics and Russification, undated, 1960s (Box 12, Folder 33)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Columbus, undated; 1939 (Box 12, Folder 34)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Counter-Reformation, undated (Box 12, Folder 35)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Danish-Portugal Voyages (Skolp), undated (Box 12, Folder 36)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Darwin and Democracy (Prof. Weissman), 1950s-1960s (Box 12, Folder 37)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Darwinism in Human Society - Mutual Aid Tradition Darwinian Ethic, undated (Box 12, Folder 38)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Denmark to 1940, 1927-1950s (Box 12, Folder 39)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Early Expansion in the Baltic, undated (Box 12, Folder 40)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Educational Calendar, undated (Box 12, Folder 41)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Environmentalism and Its Emphasis, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 12, Folder 42)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Ethics Reevaluated - Darwin to Nietzsche, undated (Box 12, Folder 43)
  - Notes and Drafts -- European Center Personnel, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Greenland, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Hansa, The, 1927-1971 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Inter-Parliamentary Union, undated; 1969 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Larsen-Bobi, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Livonian Collapse, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Miscellaneous Draft, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Miscellaneous Early Typed Draft, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Missions and Imperialism, undated; 1967 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Napoleonic Period and Carl Johan to 1844, undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Nationalism, 1920s-1980s (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Neutrality Tradition - Maritime Problems, 1937-1964 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Norway to 1940, 1933-1958 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Philosophy, History, Sociology - Reaction to Positivism, 1948-1962 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Paul Christian Sinding, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Power Adjustment Around 1900, undated (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Psychology and Social Psychology, undated (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Reformation, undated (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Romanticism, 1930s-1980s (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Schleswig and the Peace Treaty (1 of 2), undated (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Schleswig and the Peace Treaty (2 of 2), undated (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Schleswig-Holstein Issue, 1954-1970 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Section I Original, undated (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Sofus Larsen Hypothesis, undated (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Survey, undated (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Sweden to 1940, circa 1940-1950s (Box 13, Folder 26)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Swedish Bid for Empire, 1950s-1960s (Box 13, Folder 27)
  - Notes and Drafts -- The Teutonic Order, circa 1955-1968 (Box 13, Folder 28)
  - Notes and Drafts -- Vikings, 1967-1980 (Box 13, Folder 29)
  - Notes and Drafts -- World War II and Slavic Hegemony, undated; 1951 (Box 13, Folder 30)
  - Norway Reports -- Rough Drafts and Miscellaneous, 1 of 2, circa 1940-1945 (Box 13, Folder 31)
  - Norway Reports -- Rough Drafts and Miscellaneous, 2 of 2, circa 1940-1945 (Box 13, Folder 32)
  - Oder-Neisse Line, 1951-1967 (Box 13, Folder 33)
  - Paul Christian Sinding Journal Article, 1960 (Box 13, Folder 34)
  - Publication Listings (Northern Europe) (1 of 3), 1927-1938 (Box 13, Folder 35)
  - Publication Listings (Northern Europe) (2 of 3), 1938-1958 (Box 13, Folder 36)
  - Publication Listings (Northern Europe) (3 of 3), 1958-1965 (Box 13, Folder 37)
  - Scandinavia Miscellaneous, 1945-1963 (Box 13, Folder 38)
  - Scandinavian Reports, 1942-1943 (Box 13, Folder 39)
  - Scandinavian Reports (1 of 2), 1943 (Box 13, Folder 40)
  - Scandinavian Reports (2 of 2), 1943 (Box 13, Folder 41)
  - Scandinavian Reports, 1943 September-November (Box 13, Folder 42)
  - Scandinavian Reports, 1943 November-1944 March (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Scandinavian Reports, 1944 March-May (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Speech Notes, 1934-1942 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Thoughts on Current Issues, 1967-1984 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Translation of "Niccolo Machiavelli" by Hans E. Kinck, undated (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Watergate, 1973-1974 (Box 19, Folder 15)
- Series VIII: Films, circa 1937-1954
  Series VIII contains film footage of different cities and countries around the world including Paris, San Francisco, and Mexico. Also included is footage of the 1939 World's Fair.
  - England's Coronation, circa 1937
    Format
    Original format: 16 mm film
  - Paris, undated
  - New York World's Fair, 1939; cuid18777 (Box Shared University Archives 017, 16mm film reels ref1658)
  - Golden Gate International Exposition, San Francisco, circa 1939-1940; cuid18778 (Box Shared University Archives 017, 16mm film reels ref1660)
  - Cottonwood, Iowa, 1940; cuid18779 (Box Shared University Archives 017, 16mm film reels ref1662)
  - England's Coronation, 1937
    Original format: 16 mm film, b&w
  - Home Folks, 1938; cuid18780 (Box Shared University Archives 017, 16mm film reels ref1666)
  - People Outdoors in Suburbia, 1940; cuid18781 (Box Shared University Archives 017, 16mm film reels ref1674)
  - Europe, 1954; cuid18782 (Box Shared University Archives 017, 16mm film reels ref1668)
  - Mexico, 1937; cuid18783 (Box Shared University Archives 017, 16mm film reels ref1670)
  - Washington Square, 1953; cuid18784 (Box Shared University Archives 017, 16mm film reels ref1672)
  - Home Movies, unknown; 16 mm film reel (Box Shared University Archives 134, Reel 31142067184559)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Handwritten note on canister reads "color silent answer print"
  - Home Movies, 1937-1954; 16mm film reel (Box Shared University Archives 134, Reel 31142067184567)
  - DPX Compilation Film, cuid18785
    This digital file is a compilation of eight digitized films from this series packaged as a Digital Picture Exchange (DPX) file.